Finding Aid for G. Mennen Williams Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Sound recordings
  - Audio-tapes
    - 1966
      - Transcription of program at University of Detroit Field House upon occasion of campaign visit of Sen. Robert F. Kennedy, featuring Jerome P. Cavanagh, John Conyers, Zolton Ferency, and G. Mennen Williams, October 29, 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 7 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 126)
      - Sen. Robert F. Kennedy speaking in praise of GMW at political meeting at University of Detroit Field House, October 29, 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 3.75 ips, 4 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 127)
      - GMW speaking (side 1) to employees of the Wayne County Juvenile Court and at a Democratic Rally in Southfield, and GMW interview (side 2) on WJR, Detroit radio station, October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 3.75 ips, 5 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 128)
      - Robert Griffin appearance on Lou Gordon television program, October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 3.75 ips, 5 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 129)
      - GMW-Robert Griffin debate, October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 3.75 ips, 5 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 130)
      - Endorsement by Robert Kennedy of GMW for U.S. Senate, October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); ca. 3 min., 7.5 ips, 4 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 131)
      - Radio spots (Williams for U.S. Senate); 3 cuts: "Pursuit of Peace", "Education", and "Omnibus", October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); ca. 3 min., 7.5 ips, 5 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 132)
      - Radio spots (Williams for U.S. Senate); 4 cuts (including Edward Kennedy endorsement), October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); ca. 4 min., 7.5 ips, 4 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 133)
      - Radio spots (Williams for U.S. Senate), October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 4 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 134)
      - Campaign song, "He's the Man for Us" sung by Johnny Desmond, October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 4 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 135)
      - Campaign statements and speeches, September-October 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 3.75 ips, 2 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 136)
      - Interview with GMW for Voice of America broadcast, December 9, 1966; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 7 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 137)
    - 1968
      - Tribute to GMW on TULC program, Freedom Forum, upon occasion of his becoming Ambassador to the Philippine Islands, June 16, 1968; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 7 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 138)
    - 1970
      - Announcement of GMW decision to run for the Michigan Supreme Court, May 19, 1970; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 6 in. (Box 5-S)
        (Tape 139)
      - Campaign spots, October 1970; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel tapes); 7.5 ips, 5 in. (Box 5-S)
        (2 cuts: 30 sec., 10 sec.)
        (Tape 140)
    - 1970s and 1980s
      - Unprocessed - primarily audiocassettes of 1970s and 1980s. (Box 6-S)
      - Lecture seminar of G. Mennen Williams, entitled "An American Ambassador in the Philippines", 1977 December 02; 2 Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
        - [Tape 1, Side 1], [86393-SR-141-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1; Covers the whole tenure 1968-69, with special attention to his preparation and first arrival as Ambassador. Questioners, people mentioned, topics outlined in detail on attached sheet.)
        - [Tape 1, Side 2], [86393-SR-141-2]; mp3 file; (Tape 1; Covers the whole tenure 1968-69, with special attention to his preparation and first arrival as Ambassador. Questioners, people mentioned, topics outlined in detail on attached sheet.)
        - [Tape 2, Side 1; no Side 2], [86393-SR-142-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 2; Covers the whole tenure 1968-69, with special attention to his preparation and first arrival as Ambassador, Questioners, people mentioned, topics outlined in detail on attached sheet.)
      - G. Mennen Williams interview with Tim Skubick and others, 1978; Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips (Box 6-S)
        - [Side 1; no Side 2], [86393-SR-143-1]; mp3 file; (G. Mennen Williams discusses his political plans in 1978, either to run for Governor again or to continue in the court system.)
      - W. S. Woodfill reminiscence, 1975 August 10; Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips (Box 6-S)
        - [Side 1; no Side 2], [86393-SR-144-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1; Interview with W.S. Woodfill who remembers the individuals he worked with on financial and business matters in Michigan.)
      - W. S. Woodfill reminiscence, [Undated]; Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips (Box 6-S)
        - [Side 1; no Side 2], [86393-SR-145-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 2; Interview with W.S. Woodfill who remembers the individuals he worked with on financial and business matters in Michigan.)
      - W. S. Woodfill reminiscence, 1975 July 08; Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips (Box 6-S)
        - [Side 1; no Side 2], [86393-SR-146-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 3; Interview with W.S. Woodfill who remembers the individuals he worked with on financial and business matters in Michigan.)
- Scrapbooks, 1948-1987; 41 volumes
  The Scrapbook subgroup comprises 41 outsize volumes of clippings from state and national newspapers documenting Williams' career as governor, diplomat and Michigan Supreme Court Justice. In addition to newspaper clippings the scrapbooks include occasional programs and mementos from political and social events. An index to volumes 1-12 is available in the library.
  - Numbered Series, 32 volumes
    - Vol. 1, February- December 1948 (Volume 1)
    - Vol. 2, January-June 1949 (Volume 2)
    - Vol. 3, June-December 1949 (Volume 3)
    - Vol. 4, January-June 1950 (Volume 4)
    - Vol. 5, June-November 1950 (Volume 5)
    - Vol. 6, November 1950-March 1951 (Volume 6)
    - Vol. 7, March-September 1951 (Volume 7)
    - Vol. 8, September 1951-February 1952 (Volume 8)
    - Vol. 9, February-October 1952 (Volume 9)
    - Vol. 10, October 1952-April 1953 (Volume 10)
    - Vol. 11, April-November 1953 (Volume 11)
    - Vol. 12, November 1953-May 1954 (Volume 12)
    - Vol. 13, May-November 1954 (Volume 13)
    - Vol. 14, November 1954-April 1955 (Volume 14)
    - Vol. 15, April-August 1955 (Volume 15)
    - Vol. 16, August 1955-February 1956 (Volume 16)
    - Vol. 17, February-June 1956 (Volume 17)
    - Vol. 18, June-October 1956 (Volume 18)
    - Vol. 19, October 1956-May 1957 (Volume 19)
    - Vol. 20, April-May 1957 (Volume 20)
    - Vol. 21, May-December 1957 (Volume 21)
    - Vol. 22, December 1957-April 1958 (Volume 22)
    - Vol. 23, April-October 1958 (Volume 23)
    - Vol. 24, October 1958-April 1959 (Volume 24)
    - Vol. 25, April-September 1959 (Volume 25)
    - Vol. 26, September 1959-January 1960 (Volume 26)
    - Vol. 27, January-April, 1960 (Volume 27)
    - Vol. 28, May-November 1960 (Volume 28)
    - Vol. 29 Africa Trip, 1961 (Volume 29)
    - Vol. 30, November 1960-February 1961; April 1961-February 1963 (Volume 30)
    - Vol. 31, February 1963-June 1966 (Volume 31)
    - Vol. 32, June 1966-March 1967 (Volume 32)
  - Unnumbered series, 1966-1987; 9 volumes
    - Senatorial Election Campaign, 1966
      (3 vol.)
    - International Student Day, 1958
    - U.S. Ambassador to the Philippines, 1968-1969
    - 1971-1977, 1978-1979
    - 1977-1978
    - 1978
    - 1982-1985
    - 1985-1987
- State Department Files Microfilm Edition
  G. Mennen Williams served as Undersecretary of State for African Affairs from 1961-1966. In 1974, the U.S. State Department, upon request of the Michigan Historical Collections and Governor G. Mennen Williams, consented to microfilm the files of the department of African affairs during the period when Williams was assistant secretary. The procedure followed prior to microfilming is described in the memorandum from State Department officer W. Witman, which is available at the library. The result of the project is 23 microfilm reels of materials covering the period, 1960-1966.
  The researcher should be alerted to certain problems in the use of these films not fully described in the Witman memorandum. First, relatively little processing was done on the files before filming. Several reels appear to be filmed in random order. The difficulty is compounded because the film came without a meaningful inventory. Reels were described in a general manner (either "trips" or chronological") but there were no internal targets to aid the researcher. Finally, of the materials labeled as chronological, the files were filmed with the latest date first. The researcher wanting to examine files chronologically will thus have to begin at the end of a reel and work his/her way forward.
  The collection has four recognizable series plus a number of miscellaneous reels. Series I is a 1964. chronological file covering the period 1961-1966, with a gap of July 1963 to December 1964. Series II is also a chronological series. Consisting of copies of the Secretary's outgoing letters, this series is of a more personal nature and includes thank you letters and letters of congratulation. This series also has a gap of July 1963 to December 1964. Series III is the files of the Secretary's special assistants, primarily John T. Abernethy, but also including Edward J. Chesky and Alexander L. Wiener, Jr. Series IV relates to Governor Williams' several trips through Africa. Series V is miscellaneous.
  - Series I: Correspondence
    - January 19, 1961-January 25, 1962 (Reel 1)
    - January 25-November 7, 1962 (Reel 2)
    - November 7, 1962-June 28 1963 (Reel 3)
    - January 4-July 15, 1965 (Reel 4)
      (also includes correspondence from Series II, Oct. 6, 1965-March 24, 1966)
    - July 15, 1965-January 28, 1966 (Reel 5)
  - Series II: Correspondence
    - January 11-May 24, 1961 (Reel 6)
    - May 24, 1961-April 6, 1962 (Reel 7)
    - April 9, 1962-June 23, 1963 (Reel 8)
    - January 5-September 24, 1965 (Reel 9)
    - October 6, 1965-March 24, 1966 (Reel 4)
      (part of Series II was filmed at end of Series I on reel 4)
  - Special Assistant's File
    - August 3, 1965-March 28, 1966 (Reel 9)
    - October 26, 1961-April 10, 1962 (Reel 10)
      (also includes personnel appointment files, 1951-1963)
    - April 10, 1963-August 19, 1963 (Reel 11)
    - August 19, 1963-July 20, 1965 (Reel 12)
    - circa 1962-1965 (Reel 13)
      (miscellaneous files)
  - Series IV: Trip Files
    - Trips, 1962-1966 (Reel 14)
      - Nigeria, August-September 1965 (Reel 14)
      - Togo, July-September 1965 (Reel 14)
      - Ghana, 1965 (Reel 14)
      - Ivory Coast, July-September 1965 (Reel 14)
      - Liberia, July-September 1965 (Reel 14)
    - Notebook, January 1966 (Reel 14)
      (Vietnam Peace, working papers)
    - Chief of Missions Conference, May 1965 (Reel 14)
    - Gambian Independence Ceremonies, February 1965 (Reel 14)
    - European trips, 1962-1963 (Reel 14)
    - Geographical File
      (includes substantive exchanges between GMW and U.S. ambassadors)
      - Algeria (Reel 14)
      - Angola (Reel 14)
      - Burundi (Reel 14)
      - Cameroon (Reel 14)
      - Central African Republic (Reel 14)
      - Chad (Reel 14)
      - Congo (Reel 14)
      - Dahomey (Reel 14)
      - Ethiopia (Reel 14)
      - Gabar (Reel 14)
      - Ghana (Reel 14)
      - Guinea (Reel 14)
      - Ivory Coast (Reel 14)
      - Kenya (Reel 14)
      - Liberia (Reel 14)
      - Libya (Reel 14)
      - Madagascar (Reel 14)
      - Nyasland (Reel 14)
      - Mali (Reel 14)
      - Mauritania (Reel 14)
      - Morocco (Reel 14)
      - Mozambique (Reel 14)
      - Niger (Reel 14)
      - Nigeria (Reel 14)
      - Rhodesia and Nyasaland (Reel 14)
      - Rwanda (Reel 14)
      - Senegal (Reel 14)
      - Sierra Leone (Reel 14)
      - Somali Republic (Reel 14)
      - South Africa (Reel 14)
      - Sudan (Reel 14)
      - Tanganyika (Reel 14)
      - Togo (Reel 14)
      - Tunisia (Reel 14)
      - Uganda (Reel 14)
      - Upper Volta (Reel 14)
      - Zambia (Reel 14)
      - Northern Rhodesia (Reel 14)
      - Miscellaneous (Reel 14)
    - Briefing Book, February-March 1961 (Reel 15)
      (Arranged by country)
    - Memoranda and clippings (Reel 15)
    - Trips, 1963 (Reel 16)
      (includes memos, reports, press releases, and correspondence)
    - Trips, 1961-1963 (Reel 17)
    - Trips, 1961-1962 (Reel 18)
  - Series V: Miscellaneous
    - Signature File, 1961-1964 (Reel 19)
      (in no apparent order; includes incoming letters to Williams and his special assistant; also clippings)
    - Signature File, 1961-1963 (Reel 20)
      (in no apparent order, includes material on trips; correspondence and other papers detailing positions of U.S. Senators and Congressmen with respect to Africa; this last group of material is arranged in reverse alphabetical order, letters B-H only)
    - Signature File, 1961-1963 (Reel 21)
      (includes personnel files, thank yous, and special assistant's correspondence)
    - Memoranda and reports, 1962-1964 (Reel 22)
      (much substantive material, but in no apparent order)
    - Papers, 1963-1965 (Reel 23)
      (largely concerning problems of the civil rights struggle in America in relation to U.S.-Africa foreign; includes files on the American Negro Leadership Conference of Africa)